I'm going to speak today about the relationship between science and human values
now it's generally understood that the questions of morality questions of good and evil and right and wrong are questions about which science officially has no opinion
it is a start that science can help us get what we value
but I can never tell us what we ought to value and then consequently most people I think most people probably here think that science will never answer the most important questions in human life
questions like what is worth living for what is worth dying for what what constitutes a good life
so I'm going to argue that this is
illusion of the separation between science and human values is an illusion and actually quite a dangerous one at this point in human history
now it's often said that science cannot give us a foundation from reality and human values because science deals with fact
and facts and values seem to belong to a different sphere
it's often thought that there's no description
of the way the world is
they can tell us how the world ought to be
but
this is quite clearly untrue
but values are
certain kind of fact
that they are facts about thewell-beingof conscious creatures
why is it that we don't have ethical obligations towards rocks
why don't we feel compassion for rocks
we don't think rocks can suffer and if we're more concerned about our fellow primates
then we are about insects as indeed we are
we think they are exposed to a greater range of potential happiness and suffering now the crucial thing to
notice here is that this is a factual claim
something we could be right or wrong about it if we've missed construed the relationship between biological complexity and the possibilities of experience well then
we could be wrong about the inner lives of insects
and there's no
notion no version of
human morality and human values that i've ever come across that is not at some point reducible to a concern about conscious experience
as possible changes
even if you get your values from religion
if you think that good and evil ultimately related to conditions after death either to an eternity of happiness with God eternity of suffering in hell
we're still concerned about consciousness and its changes and to say that such changes can persist after death is itself a factual claim which of course may or may not be true
now to speak about the conditions ofwell-beingand this life for human
we know
there's a continuum of such facts
that is possible to live in a failed state
everything that can go wrong does go wrong where mothers cannot feed their children
strangers can not find the basis for peaceful collaboration where people are murdered indiscriminately and we know that it's possible to move along this continuum
something quite a bit more I did like I was to a place where a conference like this is even conceivable and we know
we know that there are
wrong answers to how to move
in this space
adding color to the water be a good idea
probably not
good idea for everyone to believe in the evil eye so that when bad things happen to them they immediately blame their neighbors
not that they are truth to be known about how human communities flourish whether or not
we understand these truths and morality relates to these truths so in talking about values we are talking about facts
now of course our situation in the world can be understood at many levels there's the from the level of the genome on up to the level of economic systems and political arrangements but if we're going to talk
how about human wellbeing we are of necessity talking about the human brain because we know that our experience of the world and of ourselves within it is realized in the brain whatever have
after death even if
the sewer
bomber does get seventy two virgins in the afterlife in this life his personnel
it's rather unfortunate personality is the product of his brain cancer
and the contributions of culture of culture changes us as indeed it does it changes us by changing our brains and therefore the whatever cultural variation there is in how human beings flourish can at least in principle the understood in the context of a mature science of the mind neuroscience psychology etc
what I'm arguing is that value is reduced to facts the facts about
a conscious experience
just beans