I'm going to speak today about the relationship between science and human values
now it's generally understood that the questions of morality questions of good and evil and right and wrong are questions about which science officially has no opinion
it is a start that science can help us get what we value
but I can never tell us what we ought to value and then consequently most people I think most people probably here think that science will never answer the most important questions in human life
questions like what is worth living for what is worth dying for what what constitutes a good life
so I'm going to argue that this is
illusion of the separation between science and human values is an illusion and actually quite a dangerous one at this point in human history
now it's often said that science cannot give us a foundation from reality and human values because science deals with fact
and facts and values seem to belong to a different sphere
it's often thought that there's no description
of the way the world is
they can tell us how the world ought to be
but
this is quite clearly untrue
but values are
certain kind of fact
that they are facts about thewell-beingof conscious creatures
why is it that we don't have ethical obligations towards rocks